A Guide to the Abisha Ruckman Gum letters, 1861-1869
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Abisha Ruckman Gum letters, 1861-1869
Library of Virginia
54281
.225 cubic feet (1 box)
Abisha Ruckman Gum
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harold L. Crist, Arbovale, West Virginia
Biographical Information
Abisha Ruckman Gum was born to Isaac and Mary Jane Ruckman Gum on 16 July 1842 in Highland County, Virginia. Abisha served in Company F, 25th Virginia Infantry, Confederate States Army between the years 1861 and 1864. Abisha died while imprisoned at the Point Lookout Prison, Maryland, on 24/25 October 1864. He is buried in the Point Lookout Confederate Cemetery, located on Point Lookout Road about two miles south of Scotland, Maryland. Abisha's home was in the Mill Gap area of Highland County, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1861-1869, written to and from Abisha R. Gum (1842-1864), while serving with the 25th Virginia Infantry, Company F. The letters were written between Abisha and his family including his father, Isaac, and sisters, Nancy and Priscilla E. Gum, of Mill Gap, Higland County, Virginia. Topics include news of friends and family, battles, cost of food, fellow soldiers who were injured or killed, and his feelings on the war. Includes mentions of the Battle of Gettysburg, battles in Maryland, and Culpeper County, Virginia. Includes transcriptions provided by the donor. Also includes two letters, 1867, 1869, from Nancy Wade (1816-1882) of Pettis County, Missouri, to members of the Gum family.
Abisha R. Gum letters and transcripts are available online. Abisha R. Gum biographical and genealogical information, service record, casualties at the battle of Winchester and Cedar Creek, and Nancy Wade letters, 1867, 1869, are not available online.
Contents List
- Letters, 1861 (Folder 1)
- Letters, 1862 (Folder 2)
- Letters, February-July 1863 (Folder 3)
- Letters, August-November 1863 (Folder 4)
- Letters, 1864 (Folder 5)
- Letter, 20 March 186- (Folder 6)
- Envelopes (Folder 7)
- Nancy Wade letters, 1867, 1869 (Folder 8)
- Undated verse (Folder 9)
- Biographical and genealogical information on Abisha Gum (Folder 10)
- Abisha Gum service record, Company F, 25th Virginia Infantry (Folder 11)
- Casualty lists for the battles of Winchester and Cedar Creek, 19 September and 19 October 1864 (Folder 12)
- Transcriptions of letters, 1861-1864 (Folder 13)
- Photocopies of letters, 1861-1864 (Folder 14)